Welcome back everybody to the sixth
episode of active inference insights. I
am back today with another fantastic
guest, Adam Safron.
Adam is a postdoctoral research fellow
at Johns Hopkins Center for Psychedelic
and Consciousness Research
with deep roots in the active inference
framework. Adam's work has explored the
nature of preferences and motivation,
mindfulness, consciousness, agency, and
psychedelics. In addition to this, he
might well be our guest thus far who has
written a paper titled What is orgasm?
And deadlifted 280 kilos for multiple
reps.
Uh in sandals, may I add. Uh note, by
the way, that these two domains need not
be related. Adam, thank you so much for
joining me and uh welcome to the show.
So good to
I know. I'm I'm really glad you could
join us. And as I said, I mean, uh I'm
always blown away by the diversity of
interests and and research topics that
our guests bring to the table. So it'll
be great because I think we're we're
going to have a wealth of things to
cover.
The first thing I wanted to ask is about
the body. Um
you write in um one of your papers,
"Bodies represent near-ideal initial
systems for learning and inference, with
this prototypical object and causal
system providing basis for further
modeling."
I wanted to ask cuz I've been interested
in what Yaqub Howe called the evidential
boundary. Where can we kind of circle
off the internal and the external uh
with respect to Markov blankets and
active inference?
So I wanted to get your take on whether
you thought that
What do you think of
the body? Is it a
prior that we could say the mind, the
cognitive system uh
is incorporating uh
in its in its sort of uh predictive
schema, or is it itself an object of
inference that the mind um you know,
conducts probabilistic reasoning over?
Yes.
To which one? Well,
so
Well, um
So the idea I was saying to you
in that particular paper, um
I'm trying to provide account of
basically how core knowledge gets uh
loaded into minds. So you know, like we
need something like core knowledge, but
what's a biologically plausible account
of how we might arrive at it? And so
then the idea is you're basically using
um
the body as um basically a way of
structuring structuring um
learning curricula to make them
tractable um
for a computationally bound system and a
um
with limited learning opportunities.
Like making the most with the least. And
the idea is you create basically the
body acts as a near um ideal like
training wheel system to figure out
where the conditions for inference are
fruitfully constrained. And then you can
use that in the structure learning
process. Sure.
And so um you can think of it as So the
body would be both um in a way an
evolutionary prior.
And that the specific ways in which it's
some uh
you know, like for instance, like the um
Rolf Pfeifer, I think, speaks really
well to this in terms of like the way
that the the the limited shoulder, the
the range of what the the mobility of
the shoulder joint, for instance,
already would would make your your arm
go out in front of you and then like be
more likely to grab things and where
they're like Well, look, right there at
the right distance for me to both
manipulate them and to observe them. And
so those would be the kind of like
evolutionary priors you might expect,
but it's like a in the bootstrapping
process it would be um
Yeah, you could also think of it though
as um
like core knowledge to get to there,
it would be
may maybe not necessarily an
evolutionary prior, but it a very
reliably learnable posterior.
So or an empirical prior. Um
So yeah, I I think depending on like but
it might be so reliably learned and so
canalized eight ways from Sunday that it
might as well be an evolutionary prior,
even though there is like this mediation
by the learning that takes place, but
it's basically in the bag because you
did it because nature did it so well.
Um so whether you would call it a prior
or a posterior, um depends on your
perspective. And then um some other
people who've um
kind of talked to the body as a prior,
like uh Micah Allen had a good paper. Uh
the the body as prior talking about the
way in which, for instance, um our
interoceptive states as particularly
stubborn predictions would help to make
sure that like the whole like generative
model is basically uh orbiting around
allostasis. And so like
So yeah.
Yeah, does it make Does Does it make
intellectual sense to you to carve a
dividing line uh like an evidential
boundary? Or can we Is it Is it more
sort of elegant to just say it's
philosophically vague?
So yeah, so um
So I guess like in that tradition of
like the So like the body as first
prior,
um there's also like the work with like
um
Ana Chenitz and um others where it's
like
us starting like mentalizing
homeostasis, where it's like you you
you're um
part of this learning curriculum is uh
multi-agent and uh
coupled. Like like we're starting out
within someone else's bodies and then
even when we're on the outside, we we
might as well be because we're so
dependent. And so like uh
And within like this also this um um
Rolf um Pfeiferian context or the
roboticist um in the
overlap with like Rodney Brooks also um
similar kind of thinking with the world
as its own best model and then
like emergence is a morpho and and a lot
of the lifting being done by
morphological intelligence.
Um
you know, even when you know, you're on
the outside of the womb, uh you're uh
intensely coupling with others in an
extended mind sense. So it's like uh
It seems like
you definitely
uh you can't just say take it like at
the body boundary
and you know, the mind stops. You know,
it's
um
Yeah. this account. This is a really
interesting avenue I've been thinking
about um
Clark and Chalmers' '98 extended mind
hypothesis paper in in the lens of
active inference.
And I've been sort of informed in my
thinking by two people. Um
I've really mentioned one of them on the
earlier podcast, which is Manuel
DeLanda.
And his most recent book um
uh
what's it called? Material
Phenomenology. He gives us sort of uh
mechanistic account of vision. And he
critiques the enactivist tradition on
this count that basically what they want
to call an intrinsic relation, i.e., the
coupling itself is constitutive of the
identity.
So in the coupling between agent and
arena, you actually form the definition
of agent and arena. He criticizes that
that that what actually that really is
is a causal extrinsic relationship. So
that's one strand. And then the other is
Thomas Metzinger.
And Thomas uh
we'll do the podcast with Professor
Friston.
And he spoke about how the notion of
enaction might be quite misleading cuz
it kind of implies that there is there
might be a subtle reification of a
Cartesian ego where you have A enacting
B.
So I want Yeah, I wanted to kind of pick
your brain on that because it's
interesting you brought up extended
cognition and the fact that the mind
might it's identity might go beyond the
the remits of the body.
Are we Are we at in danger there of
invoking what DeLanda calls an intrinsic
relation where really what we're looking
at is just causal connections uh and
we're not we shouldn't actually be
mistaking that for identity relations?
I'm not sure. Um and then you know, I
might also um
Like in that paper I imagine I like kind
of antagonized more than a few people
and actually kind of like say going uh
neo-Cartesian in a way. Like suggesting
like something like
quasi-homuncular
and
it asks is like as like essential ways
like understanding like agents in the
relations to the world in terms of like
the way they're situated. And that um
internal having an internalized
representation
uh
pegged according to this uh reference
frame of an observer um from an
egocentric perspective uh
would do a lot of like heavy lifting in
the process of structure learning and
making things tractable. Um so
um
The Yeah, so it's like I guess
Yeah.
You might have to like loop around a few
times, you know, in terms of
getting me to talk properly, but uh
I guess the way I'm thinking it's like
like mind as model
has to be like extended. And it's like
the um
the ways in which like the affordance
landscape is so dependent on these
couplings to to like to to go too
internalist is in a way miss the point
Right.
about what lets you do anything. What
let you have your nature, but I I do
have sympathies for the internalist
account in terms of making room for
things like um representation so that
you can do things like um offline
learning and imaginative planning and
like, you know, basically like the world
is its own best model. Whenever
possible, it's morphological compute a
compute, you know, uh emergence com um
morpho uh uh, you know, from a um
the the couplings of the organism's
environment, mhm, you know, put don't
just like
push your predictions down to to the
lowest level of like the brain, push
them out into the environment. Yeah,
yeah, yeah. Yeah, yeah. Well, exactly, I
mean, that's that that I guess was the
the question that I wanted to come to,
which is um so, it's all very nicely
interwoven.
You're right. You you invoke this notion
of the kind of quasi homunculus systems.
Um and you mentioned the frame problem,
uh
which is a really interesting to me,
which is kind of how can we be uh
intelligent in an ignorant manner?
Uh how can we zero in on personal
information in the world given the
preponderance of
sense data? Intelligent in an ignorant
manner, I love that. Um thanks. It's
it's it's uh it's not mine. I'll shout
out John Vervaeke. I mean, he's the one
who's kind of outlined the frame problem
to me more than more than anyone else.
You So, I this is kind of a leading
question because I have a sense of where
you're how you're going to answer it
given what you just said.
But can the frame problem be solved by
just kind of a single conscious
homunculus at the tip of the prefrontal
cortex? And if not, how deep do these or
how deep do you imagine that these quasi
homuncular or non all these mindless
cognitive agents, as Manuela Landauer
would call them, how deep do they go
towards the skin?
I'm sorry. I don't know I've gone right
into the deep end on these, but why not?
No, no, it's good.
Um
So, it seems like
the
extended and active nature of
of minds um helps to curtail like frame
problems and that you're you're you're
always like in the world in particular
ways. And if like
your coupling with the environment is
creating basically like is basically
like
in a way creating like a an enslaving
center manifold for the whole system
that you you you always have to keep
coming back to to stay on top of this
action not just you just stay on top of
this action perception cycle and on top
of um this inter- interchange. Um you
know, the the full scope of relevance is
if you're always kind of like being
brought back home and grounded.
It it in this common task of cybernetic
control uh that that seems to like take
some of like the I don't know if it I
don't know if it quite defangs the frame
problem, but it helps to curtail a
little bit.
Um the
uh and so, then
you know, but in terms of also like
taking the
the the range of um
you know, potential relevant
affordances, it's still, you know, a a
big space.
Um but still, you know,
the idea of like orbiting it around
um
an agent's model of itself and its
interaction with the world
um
I don't know how far um
homuncular, for instance, representation
gets you with respect to that, but in in
a way it um with the idea of like
basically one of the core things that
you're modeling is the living body.
The idea being the center of your
experience this um uh
you know, so so, the homunculus I guess
we would So, let let's unpack
homunculus. So, like the the thing that
people are worried about would be,
right, a homuncular regress, where it's
like
there's a little man in the head that's
doing the observing and if explain
things. And so, the reason I kind of um
start to push on this issue of like
trying to resurrect homunculi and things
like Cartesian theaters
is the idea is that the the folk
intuition and and like is coupled to the
phenomenology in a way that actually
might reflect the data structures, might
actually reflect the um way the system
is organ-
reflect the principles of the
controller.
Right. And and so, um
you know,
the the importance of taking your
perception and giving it a coherent
perspectival reference frame. So,
something, you know, theater-esque in
terms of, you know,
having like the right geometric
relations of the things in the world and
their relationship to you.
But then also, for instance, though, the
idea of like an observer that helps that
watches the screen um the sense of uh um
your embodiment as a central data
structure
um being in close uh communication uh
with basically uh the systems by which
you would do visual perceptual synthesis
cuz you know, you're um
you know, what your body is doing will
inform what you're likely to be what it
means what's coming in on your retina
and or
the visual spatial So, the somatospatial
should tell you about the visuospatial
and vice versa.
And it's interesting that in robotics,
these are actually the primary data
structures they use. So, like in the
collaborations um I've done with like
Tim Verbeelen and Ozan Cakmak, like um
in their latent slam systems
one of the primary things for situating
the robot in the world is basically a
conjunction of views and poses.
It's like and and and they're almost
like one data structure in that it's,
you know, one of the best
you know, where I'm looking, you know,
where where I'm where my sensors are
oriented
are going to be highly informative for
what I'm looking at and also just where
my the way my body is configured um I
don't think this quite gets in
this isn't quite brought into their
systems, but you know, the range of
relevant affordances, what am I likely
to be seeing? Well,
your the your uh
what your body is doing will be highly
relevant to that also. And so, the
mutual information should be very
strong, closely coupled.
Right.
Yeah, it it it it kind of brings me back
to the to the first question, I guess,
which is I mean, I could probably reword
that now using the terms you've just
said. I mean,
I think internal and external and active
inference can be considered a
a kind of relative misnomer
um because
if, you know, I I like Maxwell's
re-wording of it as uh tracking and
tracked or modeling and modeled. I think
that's quite an effective way of
re-shifting the focus here.
So, I guess the way of re-wording that
question is
you know,
are we
in invoking a homunculus in the
Cartesian theater, are we at risk
therefore of kind of thinking that
there's a a genuine ontological
homunculus which is conducting
variational Bayesian inference uh
and and and has a model
um
over which it does computations?
I think like that rubs
a lot of people the wrong way because
for a lot of people it's just dynamical
systems.
Um
and so,
you know,
do these kinds of questions actually
call
into question the more fundamental
um dichotomy of tracking and tracked and
distinct ontologies, distinct entities
in the world?
Potentially. Um and the
I So, yeah, I
maybe I'm asking for too much, but I
want to have it all. I want to have um I
don't know what you say uh uh
uh
enactive couplings in the streets and
like re- editions and
re-coupled good sheets, you know, like
um the you know, to to the extent
possible like you know,
there's even no need to appeal to like
some sort of model representation for
much of what I'm describing is like
mutual contextualization of like these
different sensory systems in terms of
they're already coordinated just by
having a certain situation on the body
itself and in the world in the way like
the um
the information is cascading in the
context of the enactive coupling. And
so, there's like there's a sense, you
know, the the the the model of the agent
is extended into the world. Its mind is
extended already there. And a lot of
like the the work I'm talking about, we
like the homunculus is the body itself.
There's no need for like an initial
representation of it. Um I do though
suggest we might have though um you
know,
such basically a
uh a data structure, you would say, or
um and and maybe even um
potentially involving
uh
Yeah, I I I
I I put this forward basically as a kind
of prediction
that like
nothing rides on in the sense of like
uh
if I'm wrong, sure. Uh but if I'm right,
could be interesting. So, but the
specific idea is that
there might be subnetworks of the brain
that actually um have a geometric
organization about them in terms of you
might you would even have
like within cortical hub structures
potentially a um
geometric correspondences
through the manifold activity in those
networks and what's being represented.
So, you you could even get like
homuncular in terms of like the network
is almost little person-like on some
portions. And the reason you might want
to do this
is that um within geometric deep
learning, like if you give a network the
same geometry, essentially um not
necessarily like a physical network in
terms of like
Well, I guess it would be there in the
connective eventually, but like it could
be just like a dynamic emergent pattern
of um effective connectivity. But like
if the the network though has the same
structure as that which which it is um
representing or modeling or trying to
track you end up getting potentially
orders of magnitude greater efficiency.
Yeah, that's really cool. That's really
cool.
so, it's it's possible that like there
could be in addition to like most of
what we're doing is like effortless
mastery and the homunculus story you
never need representation, you never
need an internalized model and most of
it's and you would want that, too. You
know, that's
that's quicker, more efficient. But, you
might also on top of that for the sake
of things like imaginative planning,
things like having more nuanced control
of the sensory motor engagement, you
might also have representations of this
um and um
potentially even uh uh shockingly
Cartesian accounts, like in terms of
highly centralized and even kind of
looking uh
with a geometry that would that would be
uh
of a a similar shape to the body itself.
Yeah, that that's fascinating. I mean,
these uh these strange loops, as
Hofstadter would call them, are
uh seemingly never-ending. The body
having loops of itself, the body having
loops of the world. I mean, it it comes
back to I think um
kind of the cybernetic good regulator
theorem and and
the like is that saying you know, the
there's this kind of confusion. Is that
saying that all good regulators have a
model of the world or
a model of the world? And I think I
think
I don't know. I mean, I don't know
whether you think that's still a live
question in active inference. I mean, to
be honest, to be completely candid, and
yes, I'm a relative layman with a year's
experience of thinking about active
inference and not understand I think the
maths and the physics, but that's okay.
I think there's still a kind of question
there, which is
and Carl, to be honest, was quite
neutral on on it when I asked him,
which is like what is it what what what
are internal states?
Um yes, internal so so it makes sense
that internal states have
or embody have embody beliefs about the
external states. I mean, that is at the
heart of like a likelihood mapping. So,
fine.
But, is that it?
Uh is that all we're going to give them
is these beliefs? And what does it to
embody
a subpersonal belief? Is it just an
instantiate like I think people find it
very difficult to
basically move away from the physical
mechanics to the statistical mechanics.
And I think there needs to be a bridging
mechanism. So, I don't know if you had
any thoughts just on like the broader
way that and a sort of layman audience,
including myself, could
make those intuitive or those
non-intuitive distances between
statistics and physical the physical
material world a bit more intuitive.
Two is like we're working with this
account of like
you know, blankets of blankets of
blankets.
And um
I guess the way I'm interpreting it is
like a
um
internal state
internal states
coarse-graining external states and then
nested within there internal states
coarse-graining external states
so on and so forth and like a in a
header hierarchy or a heterarchy
of uh nested nested blanketed
structures. Um
And we're giving you this there's these
multiple levels of resolution that you
can unpack as needed. And so, I guess
that the thing I'm wondering is whether
like um
I like I wonder whether
a
uh
all
So, it it seems like you know, none of
it works
without
like the enactivist principles. Like
without like the um
the the the structuring of what's
happening by intelligent morphologies or
or um or without just like that um uh
the nature of the coupling of the system
and its world providing like the
grounding in the semantics um and the
interest uh none of it gets off the
ground. But, but but the story is still
it it can be told just just at the level
of like the system
and its extended phenotype as this
one single
model and like where do you draw this
boundary? What's internal, what's
external? It's like it depends on the
scale you're thinking about it.
Right. Um and so, I guess the place
where I wonder is we're going to need
internalism is when we get to
consciousness. Yes. Basically, like it's
so so like so I you know, I guess you
might even call me like a kind of like
panpsychist of a stripe and psyche in
terms of understood as like mind. But,
then when you get to like basically
consciousness in terms of something like
uh a system for we might say there is
something that it feels like to be that
system, then and for that can do things
like um imagine, for instance, in dream.
Like for for that and those elements of
experience, it seems like we're going to
have to at some point
invoke um a a number of
a a a a a we're going to need a blanket
a a a
a
a set of attractors that are internal
and can uh
basically break free of the immediate
engagement with the world. And that's
part of our experience. And so, like for
people I think to actually like account
for phenomenology, to account for like
you know, you know, like a lot of things
that that matter to us, you know,
eventually getting to you know, things
like agency, even like free will, we're
going to need to at some point um go
internalist. But, like in that process
though, you know, it's just but uh
still the story for most of evolution uh
you know,
but but still like if you go in that
direction though,
and you lose sight of the the enactivist
principles, well, then you you basically
find yourself in the same places that I
guess you could say like the mainstream
uh machine learning goes astray
sometimes. Right. You think you're going
to handle the problem just with scale or
raw compute or or you don't understand
like the kinds of
uh learning curricula you would need to
bootstrap intelligent systems or how
they would need to be deployed to to you
know,
achieve goals in the world. Um so,
uh yeah, so I
again, like I think I I think I end up
like occupying a very awkward position
that's like you know, the
um radical enactivist will be like
you know, you don't need to invoke these
things. And
like
um uh
uh
cognitivists might be like you know, oh
no, you're you're
leaning way too hard in saying that like
embodiment is necessary and you're and
you're just and
but I think that is the case though.
Like it's it's the
um
I think everyone was
kind of right and just like emphasizing
the count of what's going on. Yeah,
yeah, yeah. I mean, I I I I I haven't
staked my
my personal claim, but I don't disagree.
And I I I think that nuance is is is
always going to be right in some
fundamental sense.
Um all theories are wrong cuz they're
just wrong at different you know, at
different degrees. All metaphors are
wrong, some metaphors are useful. Right,
exactly. I mean, I I I was wondering you
know, it's funny that it's not funny,
it's interesting that you say that the
enactivist principles are necessary.
Um it'd be great to have like a pure
intel or I can't label people, but like
someone like Jakob Hohwy who
you know, if he was here, might again,
I'm not putting words in his mouth, so
it'd be curious to see what he thinks,
might ask whether it's
uh conceivable that a kind of
compute-only system could do variational
Bayesian inference um given its priors.
I mean, I think I think another useful
distinction actually to to unpack for
our audience is something that I found
really really useful, is this
distinction between uh having a sort
epistemically
viable model of the world.
So, you are actually you know, it's
descriptive. It it accounts for the
sensations that it's uh observing
or its sensations it's receiving.
And then normatively viable model of the
world, i.e. one where you aren't just
dispersing into the heat bath, but you
can maintain your own sort of
autopoietic organization.
And I'm wondering whether you think it's
conceivable to any degree whether both
sides of that equation could be
fulfilled by
a kind of sheltered off
superintelligent homunculus.
Sheltered off and and never comes into
contact?
Well, I mean, so so it it comes into
contact uh vicariously through the
Markov blanket.
So, so there are I I I'll I'll permit
active and sensory states. Um
but again, vicariously and has to do
this kind of variational Bayesian
inference um
based on its its model. And we can kind
of get into the maths of that a little
bit of like where that model comes from
in the first place.
It may not be quite what
I think we're we're driving at, but like
one thing I would wonder in terms of
like
um like saying like no, you don't need
um
you know,
things like uh
active learning to be like intelli to
um
you don't need to like
invoke things like extended mind
concepts, you don't need to invoke
things like niche construction. But,
like in theory like you could do
everything just from like uh
a smart enough Bayesian observer. Like I
guess that would that be like the
complete class theorem is like like like
uh
well, yes, like almost like has to be
the case,
but that that that in theory
you could do it that the in the
enactivist um
elements they're being appealed to, like
if you were going like in theory, if you
want to like build like a like an AGI or
something, uh you wouldn't need to. But,
then I guess the question is like if
that in theory though, like in theory
like a three-layer neural network can
compute anything, right? Right. The
question it just might have to be so big
it doesn't fit in like the universe. And
so, it's like if that in theory can't
become in practice
given like available compute available
to systems we would real we would
feasibly be able to create, then it
becomes I think a little bit moot,
although still interesting, about like
that case of like uh like is it a matter
of in principle or in practice. So,
um
Yeah, it's where philosophy has its
limits, perhaps, um
where conceivability arguments have
their limits.
You know, a question that popped up into
my mind is
bootstrapping up uh intelligent uh or,
you know, um
it kind of in vitro intelligence. Um
I think I think one question I've always
had is
the priors that um are encoded in the
generative model kind of makes sense in
this normatively viable sense. So,
people just think of homeostasis. We
have these kinds of
um
yeah, prior expectations about the
states that we expect to be in and we'll
act accordingly to to confirm that
model.
I think people might have a bit of a
difficulty
applying the same logic to
um perceptual inference.
So, perceptual inference, uh
you know, this idea that basically
you're inverting Bayes, you are trying
to derive the state from the
observation.
I guess
the the question that I have is
if that's the sort of P of X given Y or
your probability of the state given the
observation, obviously that's done
through some form of the variational
Bayes, people might be asking, "Well,
where does the P of X comes from? Where
does your prior of states
before observations
um I think what might be the D tensor in
pond DP's
where does that come from? Like is that
encoded in the phenotype in the same way
that homeo homeostatic uh imperatives
might be?
Mhm.
Or yeah, or is it the
the D matrix or the like, you know, how
it's the Yeah, I think it's the D
matrix. Again, I'm not a
computationalist by any stretch of the
imagination.
your specific initialization within the
environment and like
getting the ball rolling, the
Yes, exactly. Exactly. It it's you know,
it
So, it it's like
it seems like like it's like we know
like without the inductive biases, like
none of it works. The structural
learning is just impossible.
Mhm. You know, with without the
evolutionary priors, without like some
sort of like, you know, intelligent
initialization. I guess the place where
um
I tend to have a I guess like a
heterodox view
in that like it's like well, I grant
like you may need something like core
knowledge. We need basically those
certain priors to to lean on. Um I tend
to think that
um
evo like natural selection had fat
fingers when it came to like like doing
the design. Uh like both in terms of
like potential complexity mismatches
between inherited information and then
like what comes afterwards, but also due
to like in like not just like in
uh
Yeah, you know, you
what we would you know, people will
sometimes refer to like the difference
in complexity between like the genome
and the connectome, for instance. Yeah,
but obviously, you know, the genome, you
know, you give it the the epigenome and
there's a lot more inheritance in that
like just in like the cell like a lot
there's a lot of heritable elements that
that go off. So, the question is like
But, even then there does seem to be
some difference in like
you squeeze through the bottleneck of
like an ovum
and so, from this one cell you
reconstituted the rest in this kind of
like
kind of like autoencoding like you you
got to pass through a bottleneck here
and somehow but from this you're now
going to go kind of const reconstitute
a network of effective connect of
functional relations and effective
connections like a full like brain's
connectome. And is
you know, is there enough in there to
like buy things the way you might need
to?
Um the way I tend to like
kind of think about it is like so, one
heuristic is um you know, the more So,
like what um kind of knowledge might
what might we need? What might be the
nature of the representation or just the
instantiation knowledge? And the more
complex it is, the less likely it is
that that is in a more direct sense
uh uh specified. Yeah. So, it's like
Yeah.
You know, if we're talking about like,
you know, um so, for instance, like you
can think of like uh
there's like a prior encoded for
instance in like the the frog brain of
like the superior colliculus of like
potentially of um based on sensitivities
to luminance, it might help me like zoom
in on eyes potentially. Like that could
be an example of something or or um
uh priors about like where you expect
light to be coming from in general and
this like helps to make things
tractable. But, then let's say you're
talking about like some of like, you
know, like good old-fashioned
evolutionary psychology, like at the
other extreme like a you know, like a
cheater detection module.
Well, how the heck would you do that,
right? Yeah, yeah, yeah. So, it it's
like
how
um likely is it that you could basically
in this learning curriculum
have these lessons occur and have this
knowledge be acquired uh early enough
and the simpler it is, the more likely
it could be there early.
Um that there's um a meaningful degree
of canalization that is actually part of
natural selection. Right. Right, right.
In general, the uh
uh
claim I've been making is that uh
in order to
In order to pull this off, um a lot of
it was indirect even for a lot of the
the core knowledge people will appeal
to. Um that
you basically just needed to create a
tractable learning curriculum to get
there and what natural selection was
primarily doing was sculpting learning
curricula
using like uh the the
the body and its positioning as as a as
a large source of of leverage on this
to help um reliably acquire the
knowledge you need, but it it's still
though acquired. But,
but and how much that acquisition is
able to do that would be depend would be
um
the the the simpler it is,
the more likely you could meaningfully
make that a canalization pathway. Yeah,
yeah. That that's awesome. That's a
that's a great way of looking at it. I
It's funny. I My undergrad was in
linguistics
um and linguistics was the was the
hotbed for all of this stuff, you know,
I mean, Chomsky, really. Um Chomsky and
Chomsky's Darwin's Darwin problem, I
mean, this is like what he was talking
about in the '90s and he had to sort of
pair down what universal grammar was
because the big question was, "Okay, you
can account for you know, perhaps
principles and parameters can account
for the complexity
and creativity of language learning, but
how the hell are these hundreds of
parameters going to be encoded in the
genome?"
Well, like like in like the versions of
like Chomsky and Pinker where he's he's
going minimalist, talking about
something like Yeah, merge function,
yeah. So, then if it's just like
something like merge that's like, "Well,
sure, that's it's very plausible,
right?" Right, right, right. You can
quickly in evolution like the ways
that's been suggested. You know, and
part of like what corresponds to like
these like phase transitions we see
where all of a sudden like new orders
are coming on pretty compressed
intervals. Yeah.
But, yeah, but if you're going to like,
you know, at the other limit like things
like I guess like a I don't know,
Pinkerian like
Yes. So, then it's like
uh-oh, I that I'm not sure biology can
do that. Well, I think he may I think he
made that concession. Um Chomsky at
least. I'm not sure about Steven Pinker,
but Chomsky certainly does and as you
say, he has a minimalist program with
merge. Um
but yeah, I think a lot of linguists
might argue that he's he's kind of
abandoned that nativist project. Um But,
anyway, we need not go in that. I'll try
and get him on the pod, actually. Um
sticking on sort of
evolution, my background is not in
evolutionary biology or psychology, so
I'm I'm super keen to learn.
Um
Again, just to take a quote of yours,
uh um you say, "Much of the functional
significance of specific connections in
complex neural networks may be
inherently difficult to predict due to
the sensitivity of brackets chaotic
self-organizing systems to initial
conditions."
So,
when I hear that,
I think sure, like it it it certainly
makes sense in terms of initial
volatility probably having more of an
effect on self-organization than once
you have a kind of robust phenotype.
But, why therefore is there a
convergence within a species a phenotype
to kind of a homogeneity if there is
this kind of vulnerability to um
to chaos?
It seems like a good amount of it
I mean, that and that
a good, you know, to get
So, you see, you're having a system
which has
a
um that's massively recurrent. In terms
of like it's like
in its in the system as it develops, it
feeds back on itself and then that
influences how it feeds back on itself
and that influences. And so, there's
this potential for amplifications to
take you in a lot of different
directions, but natural selection
doesn't want you to go in any given
direction. It wants that homogeneity. It
wants you to be like well fit to be, you
know, uh have high fitness. Wants you to
be fit to your
the niches you're likely to be
encountering and to be able to, you
know, survive and
proliferate your forms in in those
circumstances. And so, you know, you
don't want to be just like open that you
want that homogeneity. But the process,
because it feeds back on the self, will
be
it should have this potential for
uh
astronomical bifurcation. So, how do you
like rein it in? You have to say.
You know,
there seems like
And so, you know, you could just say
like, you know, well, that's what the
inductive biases are. And so, you know,
let there be inductive biases and it was
good, right? But what But then they go,
"Well, well, which ones and how?"
And so,
I wonder the extent to which like a
choke points
for
um
coordination
among sub-elements of the system
such as for instance like any kind of
place you could identify something like
a bow tie motif.
Any place you can get something like
a large scale convergence-divergence,
which in general you would expect
because you need small worldness for the
sake of just efficiently getting a
system to be integrated or to have a
system be integrated at all. The
have the different components function
together. But if everything's wired if
everything's connected to everything,
that's both chaos and there's there's no
it's very inefficient. So, the idea of
like these places where things
from
broad extents
will pass through
and then providing basically an
opportunity for
enslavement. Um
some so, um so, some of this could just
be network motifs. Like you look at for
instance um
convergence onto like hub structures
that have high centrality. But also
things like if you take the value
signals like, you know, things like
dopamine or serotonin and you
have those also have a
the conditions of their release
correspond to organism scale events.
Then that could help basically
give coordination to the overall system
in reliable ways for this task of
helping the organism make it through the
world. Helping
helping the system to function. So, it's
like these these these code dependencies
and from and choke points. These um
places where you'll get um
uh functional convergence. I I I suspect
that's like
um important for keeping that divergence
from happening too much. This uh
integration into organismic significance
of
with respect to cybernetic control of
the agent pursuing its goals. And if
that has
perch if that basically
by virtue of what we're talking about
like value signals that would then, you
know, shape connections
um or or or the the the structure of the
architecture itself. If that is
positioned such that the whole system
can be so enslaved
that should help to like even though
that should basically help these
bifurcations in a way be um
not bugs, but features. And that it's
certainly resources like solenoidal flow
and explorations and like
you know, engage you like local pockets
of like high temperature search. But
then like you rein it back in for
staying on top of the action perception
cycle. And so, to kind of come back to
like consciousness, you know, for me
it's basically iterative state
estimation.
With
with the goal being basically I want to
know
a rough and ready estimate of the
relationship between the system and the
world generated quickly enough that I
can meaningfully inform and be informed
by action perception cycles on the time
scale of their formation. And so, I can
nuance that engagement, provide some
extra skillful control and surfing
uncertainty. So, it's like
um
And so, like if the primary like task of
the system is this enactive coupling I
feel like that helps to provide that
that's helps to like tame and harness
chaos rather than
having a thing sort of
bifurcate in in, you know, all the like
hyper astronomical number of dimensions
it could go.
Cool. Yeah, yeah, yeah. There's a lot
there. I mean, yeah, that's let's do the
consciousness thing. Um
I was going to jump psychedelics, but
like why don't we start even more
fundamental consciousness.
Anyone who's watched the first five
episodes or four episodes knows that I
love consciousness. It was kind of my
foray into all of this.
So, what you've given me there is a
function of consciousness. It's guiding
action perception loops. It's it's it's
kind of a likelihood mapping state
estimation.
Okay, but as you can imagine, the
follow-up question is going to be why
does it come with its phenomenal
characteristics? And and
is there something that's intrinsic is
there something that's adaptive to the
those phenomenal characteristics which
facilitate, improve, augment the
function that you've just laid out?
I think you people could still, you
know,
like they'll laugh.
They'll pull the
There's
Why can't
these functions, you know, all take
place in the dark? Why must they like
feel like anything at all?
I I don't think that that concern
is removed. I think it loses some of its
force
if
the nature of the data structure is
considered as being like specifically
the generation of
a visuospatial
and somatospatial field of experience um
precision weighted or having like with
biases rather
different areas of salience and emphasis
based on organismic need.
And like if you're basically taking like
basically the the the the thing you were
estimating is the sensorium itself.
It it it's sort of like, well, it feels
like something because like emphasis on
the fields. Like the what the data
structure is a specifically an inversion
of a generative model over the sensorium
of an embodied embedded agent. So,
that's actually what the process is
specifically doing. Now, you can still
say, "Well, why couldn't you do the
state estimation
of the system in the world in the dark?"
Exactly.
But
you know, I I I I think that it it's
that objection though I would say the
claim is that objection holds more for
theories of consciousness that forget we
have bodies.
So, you could still levy it, but I think
it's like slightly addressed by making
the primary explanandum
the
appearance of a world to a lived body.
If that is the primary explanandum and
you're specifically saying, "How might
dynamics
compute that?" Then I think it it it
takes that on a little bit more of the
why should there be something it feels
like cuz what you're specifically trying
to explain is the fields itself.
Right. Then that helps me quite
convergent with Mark Solms's sort of
affect-driven account of qualia.
This being that sort of these
fundamental affective states are um are
sort of guides in a way to
allostatic behavior.
So, whether that's the resolution of
uncertainty
um information gain
testing model parameters or actually
just minimizing variational free energy.
See, that for me was one of the first
functional explanations of consciousness
that really made me think, "Oh, that's
that's kind of viable because
I can't conceive of a feeling without it
being felt."
Um
and so, what I've been looking for is
these kind of um
it's almost like a synthetic a priori of
consciousness. It's almost like a
transcendental argument for
consciousness. Does anything like circle
back on itself so as to make
consciousness a prerequisite for the
function? And I think where you and Mark
are converging here is quite promising.
Which is that Now, someone like David uh
what someone like 1995 David Chalmers
might go, "Well,
you could just have like an offline
signal that says things are uncertain
and let's resolve that uncertainty."
Granted.
But then I take quite seriously this
this older phenomenological Heideggerian
idea that like we're beings that take a
stance on our own existence. And that's
got to be felt to some degree. Um so,
I'm wondering what you think of of
that spiel and perhaps where there's a
points of convergence with with Mark
Solms's theories.
I'd say it's very strong place of
convergence, but also divergence. The
convergence is like
you know, he's
he's bringing in life mind continuity.
He's bringing in like the necessary
interestedness of the system and also
like the the primary
of
of affect and of saying like like you're
saying like this synthetic a priori like
what do we need to even
coherently conceive of this thing where
like what's foundational? Like if you
were to doubt it, the whole like game
falls apart.
Yeah, so unless you have like unless we
get the fields in there, we're not
getting anywhere. And unless we get like
the
um
You know, and so,
the the
I guess the thing I would suggest
as as a point of divergence
would be I wonder if the specific
systems like so I guess like for for me
um
I don't necessarily take
unconscious feelings to be an oxymoron.
But
um you know, so I
he would have used words differently,
but sometimes I'll I'll think of like
one way of thinking of like
emotions and feelings almost like a very
abstract action perception cycle. Where
it's like the emotions are the global
state changes. I don't I don't think
that it like I think by the time you get
to that level of abstraction, the
difference between action perception
falls apart. But in a way though like
the the the
the change in organismic mode
to be adaptive for a particular class of
situations, whatever that is, that seems
to be roughly something like emotion
would correspond to this. And where the
organismic mode could extend beyond the
organism in terms of the emotion being
just like contained within it. But the
feeling part uh potentially being some
sort of um
uh
inference on top of that process. Right.
Some sort of tracking of that. Now, we
can use words in any way, but like I
would personally um so that's that's a
that's the way I think of it in this way
I describe thinking of it in that um
entropy paper. And then I wonder where
we whether we can have both unconscious
and conscious feelings and emotions. So
like level where like you know, we go
back down to the individual cell and the
cell is like changing into like a
sporulated mode and maybe that's like it
becoming afraid or something. Or like
extends a pillus to like exchange a
chromosome to someone else. You know, or
or rather about chromosoma a chromatid.
And that's like like a lust mode. Or
like it releases a you know, exotoxins
or is like that's like a like a like a
aggression mode or something like a rage
mode. Like and so like I I like the idea
of like you know, kind of like the work
of like Damasio who like uh Mark like
engaged with in in beautiful ways. Like
you know,
I I
the you know, I I
I love this idea. I think it's essential
for understanding like the actual
cybernetic significance of feelings and
emotions actually be coherent about
them. To actually talk about life mind
continuity. And to recognize this is an
older story than even nervous systems in
terms of like the the um the the
harmonics or the the eigenmodes of the
organ of the organism to be adaptive.
Having those to be uh
uh to give them an overall coherent
shape. But uh
for the specific systems that Mark talks
about, um I wonder whether they uh I
guess have what it takes to do the kind
of like representation game. Whether
like um they're potentially doing their
functioning um
so you know, so he'll he'll emphasize
like the periaqueductal gray.
And and as you know, being this um
integration around organismic need and
this sort of like the the way that um um
affects in order for them to in order
for these eigenmode shifts to be
coherent so that you're you're you're
not like eating and doing care at the
same time. You know, like that would be
a bad idea in a lot of circumstances.
Like you know, you don't want like you
know, mothers to eat their pups. You
know, you don't want like the this um
picking in the in the in the the the I
think I don't know if he says color
coding, but this like categorical
breakdown. Yes. I'm totally with him
functionally.
But it still seemed like those could
happen in the dark. Right. So the thing
I'm wondering is in order for them to be
given something like phenomenality that
we experience like the conscious
feelings
I'm wondering whether that requires
something like um
basically a representation into cortical
circuits. And so he'll um
and maybe even within uh
within somatospatial and visuospatial
modalities. So I make a someone
considered to be a would consider to be
a bizarre claim
that those might actually be all we have
and all other modalities are basically
uh kind of synesthetically cross-mapped
into those to be given spatial and and
temporal spatial coherence so that they
actually can be modeled and you can do
this like state estimation. So the idea
is like your interoceptive states might
actually be to to be experienced have to
be spatialized as a kind of like texture
or as a kind of like like I I feel I I
have to I have to temporalize and
spatialize that information and maybe
part of the way you do it is to
enfold them into another modality as
part of the inference. So um
but the
uh
Yes, I guess the the difference with
Mark is I'm wondering whether
the his account is like
like like right on on the functional
level,
but um the systems though
that would actually but still though
the systems he's emphasizing would be
necessary but not sufficient conditions.
In order to obtain sufficiency, they
need to basically um
enslave cortical circuits and that those
might actually be the constitutive
causal um the constitutive realizers of
experience.
Potentially by virtue of the fact that
like again we I guess we get to like
things like small worldness.
Um networks that are basically
co-located enough that they can converge
on attractors and achieve coherence
on the right time scale. The idea of
like if you're like way far like so the
idea is like if you're way far away from
like let's say like some sort of
rhythmic attractor
over um
uh
is established that's um calculating
something like your sensorium or is like
entailing something like the inversion
of your sensorium on the time scales in
which that sensorium is inverted. Um
there might be an in and an out in terms
of like who is able to get their message
in in time. And it's possible that the
systems he's identifying could be um on
the outside of it in terms of the time
scales in which that causal closure
occurs while still being completely
necessary for their functioning. I I I
just don't think we know and so the
evidence is so you know, he would then
push back and then say like you know, oh
well um the uh let's see uh
Well, no, you know, I I I lesion the
insula and the emotions are still there.
So there's your way and there's and it's
like
yes. Um but uh
I guess in a way you might you might say
that that that somewhat supports the the
that quasi-synesthetic account I just
said, but um
I basically I I I find the
uh lines of evidence that that are cited
to be um
notable but none of them are quite
convincing to me. So like so for
instance like um
uh like hydrocephalic children. Yeah.
You know, they're still showing these
rich emotive displays, but the issue is
though uh we don't know. Yeah.
Like it could be unconscious emotion.
Yeah, we can't ask them. We don't know
what it's like to be inside. Or then you
might point to like um like decorticate
rodents showing like you know, rich like
you know, adaptive emotional uh
responses and and sophisticated
behaviors. But once again
we don't know. Um
or you might like drop an electrode and
then stimulate these subcortical areas
and then you get experience and the
person reports to them. But then the
problem is
well, the cortex is intact then. And so
how do you know if when you drop that
electrode like you stimulate the
hypothalamus and then you got some sort
of rage response or a lust response was
it that that was the realizer? Or is it
as I'm suggesting that that was
basically um part of um
you know, it was
uh causally important for the whole
thing to work, but not necessarily
constitutive of the process that um
computes or realizes
the the qualia.
So it's This is cool. This is cool.
Yeah, I feel like there are two things
going on and I'd like to sort of see if
we can converge them. So one is a kind
of structural functional description
which is augmenting um
or just providing color to Mark's view
which is that we need these kind of uh
recursive loops back to the cortex and
needs to enslave the you know, the
these
uh subcortical structures need to
enslave the cortex.
Now, someone listening might go, but
that's just a further
functional structural anatomical
explanation. On the other hand, you
invoke
kind of proto
back to the homunculi, these kind of
proto-conscious agents
we've got like
whether that's a cell a cluster of cells
and so on.
And you've spoken as well about how, you
know, one of your your account of
consciousness, you know, can be cast as
a convergence of
active inference and integrated
information theory.
Um
in
you know, integrated information theory
got some
well, it got some bad press
earlier this year for being
pseudoscience. Um on for those listening
just on audio, I am doing speech marks.
Um
but one of the claims was that it was
pandering in some sense to panpsychism.
And perhaps an a cute listener might be
thinking Adam is maybe pandering a touch
to panpsychism with his idea of lustful
uh neurons.
Where do your all sympathies lie if we
take this all the broader philosophical
position? Um
where do your sympathies lie with
panpsychism and let's just say more kind
of uh I think they're called conscious
realist positions such as that of Donald
Hoffman for example.
I'll regret saying this but I think you
could call me a panpsychist of swords
still and that like um other sense of um
anything that's somehow managed to think
and coming back to the good regulator
theorem
on some level had to entail some sort of
modeling information whether it was the
the system
and its
interact with the environment was the
model or is a is a model that within it
has models
um but has to have um some sort of
tracking or predictive information
uh
that
allows it to basically reverse resist
the most uh temporarily
uh res um
uh defy the second law while serving in
a everything it does but basically that
you know you getting all mixed up and
becoming maximally probable a maximum
entropy distribution. Like how do you do
that? You somehow did something to do
that. Yeah. Sort of intelligence some
sort of thing like a Molly some sort of
predictive information had to have been
there for you to pull off something a
little bit like Maxwell's demon
demon-esque you know to to do that. And
so in that sense I I'd say I'm a
panpsychist and that like anytime we're
pointing to things any times there's
attractors um you might want to say
there's something mind-like going on
something a little bit intelligent. um
but the um
I mean you might even want to say like
some psychological kinds you know like
like we're talking about with like
talking about like the individual cells
you know rage or lust you know um like
even those might be like good ways of
thinking about them in terms of
describing their cybernetic significance
like it it it's a you know coherent
global change of state with a certain
semantics that's linked to this modeling
and so if you think of you know mind as
modeling and then
as modeling with interest and evaluate
in way you know
you might call that sentience then. But
I guess I want to reserve this word
consciousness for the it feels like
something
and I want to res and and there's
there's something that you know it feels
like from the inside to be that system
and you know so all these systems would
have a kind of uh dual aspect part of
them cuz they would entail an
information geometry. And so you could
say it's like well you know maybe
everything that exists it's just like
that's the way of describing the dual
aspect nature of them. Um I think you
could make a case for that but I still
want though
that like um basically um Okay so in
in so in integrated world modeling
theory that the thing I attempted was to
um take the major theories
um specifically focusing on integrated
information theory and the global
workspace theory and then basically use
you could say probability theory or
machine learning or this the free energy
principle but this idea of the system
modeling its environment
probabilistically as now providing the
semantics and removing the question
begging from these theories in terms of
or some of it of why there should be
something that it's like to be a complex
of integrated information or to be the
um to have fame in the brain and to be
within a global workspace and so why?
Well if what that global workspace is
doing is it's something like a very
efficient architecture
um for for like some you know
auto-encoding hierarchy if it's like an
arena for Bayesian model selection
allowing for this iterative state
estimation
well then we we're it's the questions
are somewhat less begged or if like
integrated information theory is
describing you know um uh
the nature of networks that can do
interesting forms of compute it's like
okay um
you know necessary conditions you know
likely to you know integrated
information theory they they they they
have these these axioms that are that
they look at the applied to
purportedly to all conscious experiences
and then they try to identify these mech
they postulate mechanisms that can
realize them.
And then the idea is like if you start
out going from these axioms that
characterize an experience you then
create a precise and specific mapping to
particular mechanisms that would be that
would allow for their realization. Now
you could say this system's conscious
and that one isn't and maybe even this
system is conscious in that way and not
that way.
And you know I I think it's it's really
promising but but the issue um I take is
um uh
basically um and we like like losing the
explanandum of
uh
our sensorium our our sensor our sense
world you know our embodied experience.
And so if what that uh if what a complex
of integrated information is doing
is it's basically describing a system
set up for a certain type of dynamics
within it that could enable a certain
type of um message passing and um and
and inference and you know belief
propagation inference and specifically
with the thing being entailed by such a
system would be the you know efficient
inversion of the sensorium over uh
inversion of a generative model over the
sensorium of an embodied but agent now
we're getting somewhere. So the idea is
that for the so the idea is saying okay
um
uh so I guess I'm I'm sympathetic to
both sides in viewing integrated
information theory as
um having some elements which are
unsatisfactory
um
the
but you know I I don't think it was that
particularly I don't think what happened
was particularly helpful in terms of
calling it pseudoscience and you know uh
for a variety of reasons but so so so
yeah so the basic approach is this what
if you um take the existing theories the
major ones cross-reference their claims
look for points of overlap and try to
use basically degree of convergence in
the forms of convergence and the
coherence of those stories to adjudicate
among different claims and so that was
the basic method.
And so
you could think of for instance some you
know integrated information theory will
talk about um potentially there's a
posterior hot zone as the substrate of
consciousness and you know for instance
I say that sounds about right. That for
instance like you know if basically the
posterior if you take these different
sensory hierarchies all coming together
into one multimodal hierarchy and if you
can get um basically across that system
its ability to uh loop back on itself in
a very powerful way in in a very um
you know both integrated but also
differentiated way
then that could be a that then you could
think of that as basically um that that
could entail the inversion of an of a
generative model over the sensorium of
an embodied but agent maybe that's
what's going on. You could also
potentially think of though this complex
of integrated information that has both
uh integration that where the network
properties are set up to facilitate both
integration differentiation that's
actually has a lot of correspondences to
workspaces which balance integrated
segregated functioning.
And so the idea is like that posterior
hot zone could be thought of as a fairly
global workspace.
It's you know and um
with devils in details of exactly the
kind of workspace it is and you know
with um
with me having some specific proposals.
So then like for instance uh okay so the
workspace theory they might come in with
the claim like no no you need the front
of the brain.
And so the question is well what are we
talking about exactly? Are we talking
about um
phenomenal consciousness like the actual
generation of your experiences from
moment to moment
or are we talking about your your
knowledge your of experience your your
knowledge of your experience your
awareness of that your ability to report
on them and contextualize it in
different ways?
Well then you're probably right. The
the global workspace theory is probably
right that you you need to get the
frontal lobe in the mix to do that.
Although that point though by the time
you're you're talking about things like
that
you might even need more in the frontal
lobe. We actually might be in a like an
like a extended mind account in terms of
like what actually goes into be
self-reflective. Like ways of you know
we we like we we you know use like the
environment to like offload memory to
like the way like we're so you know the
the workspace the global workspace or
play space might not even be skull bound
you know but still the
so yeah so the approach I took was
basically to say that um the different
theories were bringing important
contributions that all these brilliant
people
these are all brilliant people who given
a lot of thought and they're have
something important to say then the
question is are they maybe using words
differently? So like in that debate
earlier between like integrated
information theory the global workspace
theory you had this recent like
adversarial collaboration saying well
who's right?
But it's not clear they were using the
word consciousness in the same way.
Like integrated information theory is
talking about experience like a
phenomenality
global workspace theory sometimes it's
like illusionist sometimes they you know
they're they're more it's like more of
like a higher order thought type theory
and and and they're often times not
necessarily but they you know it's it's
usually they're talking about you know
you'd say like conscious access as
opposed to phenomenal consciousness.
And so
so then the idea is that if you're you
try to be more like like what are the
precise claims that people are making
and you dig into them a lot of the
conflict might just be people
not communicating enough. And saying
like oh I meant this by that term and
you meant that. Oh and instead of there
being just like one way we use words it
might be that like the different ways we
were using words had different tradeoffs
and maybe like to come together we have
to like add qualifiers. So instead of
like we try to say this one word means
this one thing maybe we use like um
we need to use like two or three words
to specify which world we're in and what
we're talking what what our reference
are and then the claim I make is that
once you do that um a good amount of the
conflict actually is not as um
much as it seems like it needs to be.
Like you're actually significantly, like
these different theories are actually to
a
important degree and a useful degree
talking about different things. Right.
Right, yeah. Well, you know, maybe
there's a psychological account of the
fact that scientists like at, you know,
they they might pretend that they
believe in collaborative
work, but there is
there's a there's a tendency or an
inclination towards adversarial
boundaries which are often incredibly
constraining. So, that is it's a good
point. And I think it's a good point as
well about
how much language really shapes Yeah, I
don't I don't mean this in some
Sapir-Whorf deterministic way, but
shapes the way that we view these
these models, the way we view these
debates.
I mean, I think the most I think for me
comes back to to what you're talking
about like right at the beginning that I
could look at a rock and say, "Well,
there's something kind of intelligent
going on there. It's tracking something,
you know, it's doing some kind of
variational Bayesian inference." Well, I
remember you know, I think the two most
important words for someone coming into
the free energy principle
depends on the definition of the free
energy free energy principle you like,
but my two favorite are looks like.
So, anything that has a Markov blanket
and a
you know, a steady state attractor, a
non-equilibrium steady state attractor
will look like it's conducting Bayesian
inference.
And that look that
the the question of
what it is doing, the process theory
really gets opened up once you go, "Oh,
the free energy principle is just the it
might well just be a descriptive tool."
And then we talk about active inference,
predictive processing, variational
message passing. But I think this this
looks like notion is often
forgotten.
And it's important to keep it in the
back of our mind that
yes, there is something quite miraculous
about the coherence of a stone.
Um but I guess every theory has its
miracles.
Um
and the free energy principle is not
it's it's not devoid of its axioms.
Do you think that's a kind of reasonable
thing to say?
I think so. And it's like yeah, and in
general what we're trying to do is like
you know, I guess what
minimize the number of like
you know, the 6000 as we need to call
in, the number of miracles.
And like but you know, we're going to do
like you know, like you mentioned
earlier synthetic a priori categories.
Like these things you you need some you
need something to build with, you know.
Or also in terms of like the
what we're talking about with like
evolutionary priors and like inductive
biases. Like you need to start
somewhere. You you need something must
be granted. You know, but but like but
let's try to like do the most we can
with the least. And so
um
and but but still those things that you
are granted you know, in a way like
there's a sense in which like
you know, they they might be like
they're they're the preconditions for
proceeding at all. Those are the
miracles we need to to go on. And so
there's like we end up like uh
as like for the case of like you know,
like a rock and then you could say like
you know, yeah, it looks yeah, I had a
section I put into like the like
original and and and left it in there
maybe unfortunately. Like they did like
the like the IWMC paper.
And I I I felt crazy writing it. But you
know, I think like if I like emphasize
this like looks as if
like it it feels less crazy and then
saying the rock is engaging in Bayesian
inference to exist. You know.
But I guess you know, there's a
you know, I guess you could say there's
a sense in which like
that's how it is.
At that point I guess you're almost in
like a quasi tautology.
And that like like let's say it's okay.
So, here's like the phase space
description of the rock.
And then it'll
uh I guess you could say like if you
keep looking at it
um
well, I guess with the rock though
it might be we need something like
it might not work for the rock, but it
might need the like
you need something where like that
density of the thing like you like that
you can point to it and like there's a
combination like the solenoidal flow and
gradient flow where the thing is like
picking itself back together. What is a
oil?
Well, yeah, like a drop of oil that like
like read that that grabs itself and
then Yeah, yeah, that yeah.
So, once you do that, isn't that kind of
like I guess that's Carl's like 2019
paper. Then it's like a sense of like
you could say like well, that actually
is Bayesian inference. Yes. And that
there's a like where you expect to find
it, there's a thing like as a
probability distribution. And then if
you just look at its action, it's doing
Bayesian inference.
And then they're like, "Well, is that a
tautology?" Maybe.
But um
uh
it's a damn interesting ontology
tautology.
And on time. Yeah, yeah. It's I remember
hearing Carl first on Lex Fridman's
podcast talking about a drop of oil.
Kind of my first proper exposure to free
energy and I just
What?
I just couldn't think I I I didn't
believe that drops of oil or rocks or
molecules could be so interesting.
And and you're right with you know,
um science, I don't know who said it,
but science is about making the familiar
unfamiliar. Um and we're certainly
making rocks and drops of oil pretty
unfamiliar when we're talking about them
conducting variational Bayesian
inference. There's somebody who might be
interesting to talk to. He wrote a paper
on like the world as neural network.
And so like I think he would um
potentially get to this issue of like um
is there just like a way in which like
um
you could just make like a like the
ontological claim like the the rock is
engaging like he like he would do I
think uh
a good job of like making a case for
that potential.
Okay, cool. I'll I'll I'll check out the
paper. I mean, yeah, I mean for me this
the question I literally started this
podcast with still stands, which is if
we take the drop of oil
it's it's it's kind of yes, can be seen
as calculating a posterior.
Um
but
but but does that mean like what does
that mean like what is doing the
calculation? And
what's it doing a
like it what so the the P of itself
given its environment is just really
high. I mean, once you sort of break
that down, it just becomes it seems to
me to just return back to a descriptive
account
rather than a uh process theory of what
the what the drop of oil is actually
doing. So, you know, I think
where a lot of active inference
confusion comes from is that we can't
um we can't we we we struggle
conceptually to get away from a
Cartesian ego model when we're thinking
about how we are and how the world is.
So,
it's
it's tempting perhaps to think that
there's a little homunculus within the
drop of oil grabbing itself together and
maximizing model evidence for itself.
Even Carl would not say that. No, no,
no, no. Neither And that was by the way,
I'm not saying that either, but it's um
it might be tempting for some. Let's um
let's get to psychedelics because you're
at Johns Hopkins, which is
the kind of place to be in terms of
psychedelic research. I think a useful
place to start, not only for myself, but
for our audience is people might have
a sense of the history of psychedelics
in science.
Um and the long history and the taboo
and the fact that now these experimental
studies are taking place and the taboo
is lifting.
Perhaps you could kind of give a
uh brief history, if possible, of the
history of psychedelics in science. Um
you don't have to go back to shamanic
cultures, but if you feel so inclined, I
I I shan't stop you.
I mean, that actually is a um
I'm working on a paper right now of like
the deep history of psychedelics. Like
um
going
both back to shamanic cultures, but but
before in terms of
the um
evolution of the um signaling systems
that they
appear to primarily act upon.
Uh in particular, the
5HT2A serotonin receptors. And
side of this is a agonist of
that receptor. That particular receptor
class. And so there's a paper I just
recently revised and resubmitted. Good
luck. Uh
it's called the
um albus or alter beliefs under
psychedelics which basically provide
uh this
it's providing I guess you might say
heterodox account
of psychedelics within active inference.
I read the preprint. So, uh
I'm I'm familiar.
So, so that's so I guess we'll get to
that in a bit, but this is Sure. Uh
that's like where the focus has been.
But the
current paper would be like um
why is it
that we have psychedelic experiences?
And like like what is it is there is
there like so you know, you might say
maybe in a deflationary sense you could
say that like Pinker would talk about
like
music is cognitive cheesecake.
Or it's like you know,
if you try to look for an adaptive story
about music, you could try, but it's
just like no, there isn't really one
that's like that meaningful. Sort of
like you can do the adaptive story of
like cheesecake is like it's a super
stimulus that's created because of this,
this, and the other. But like there is
no evolutionary account of cheesecake.
It's a latecomer to the scene. Sure. And
so the deflationary account of like
music would be like there's no specific
music adaptations. It's just like a
super stimulus we create for ourselves.
You know.
Uh because of other things that we need
and other aspects of our cognition. And
so with psychedelics you could say like
you know these drugs just happen to be
like you know a super stimulus that's
like created
you know maybe by plants to defend
themselves against predators in terms of
the you know you you don't want to quite
you know
you you want to
either repel and so you know maybe like
you know breaking the good regulation
like like like making the the thing do
anomalous inference inference could be
you know a good way of like
repelling your your your your predators
or you might want to potentially entice
in terms of you know there's like some
symbiosis that exist in terms of things
that that was it reindeer
I don't know if this has been
established but like you know
possibly like by consuming things like
is it like is it lichen I forget what it
is but like
I like they it might like help them to
be more like exploratory at certain
parts of their like seasonal cycle
and so then there's like a a symbiotic
relationship
and you're actually enticing
the organism to come in
but the um
yes actually that's that's a very live
question of like the deep history of
psychedelics and in the place I'm going
to
I'm trying to go in this upcoming paper
is to argue that
you know so the it seems like the
receptor system itself
might have evolved I'm claiming
um
actually in a way so so um
so the count of psychedelics
in the frenetic principle that I think
that's most well known would be called
the Rebus model relaxed beliefs under
psychedelics and the idea being that
psychedelics are relaxing your Bayesian
priors and so when your prior
expectations relaxed you are now free to
think different thoughts and be updated
by the world experience it more
profoundly and be changed by more more
profoundly and so I've been
trying to
nuance that account and saying that like
that might be
um
part of what happens
as part of like very high degrees of 5
HT2A agonism and that you do get
something like that but that might not
be the cybernetic significance of the 5
HT2A system as a control parameter
and that in many ways it might actually
be exactly the opposite
and so they first evolved with a gene
duplication event around the Cambrian
explosion around with the advent of
jawed fishes
and so one of the
speculations I make is actually and this
might be
predator prey arms races
where someone can
kill and now you have an interest in
being able to have that strong
prediction that you
used to basically
enslave your inaction and achieve that
goal
and the stronger you can make that
prediction the the the more you know
actually within limits
the more reliably you'll converge on
that goal as opposed to doing something
else
but then you might also have an interest
on the side of prey of not being the
person bitten
and so this idea of like turbocharging
the organism
doubling down on the priors potentially
as a way of allowing for specific over
suit that might have been the original
story but where does this like Rebus
account come in one of the speculations
I'm making
along with it's a
paper I'm writing in collaboration with
Sue Carter who studies oxytocin
mechanisms
and there's a follow-up paper I'm
writing with um
before the other one is published with
Matt Johnson
but um
is that actually um
orgasm and birthing
might have been the original psychedelic
experiences
and that actually so you're basically
relaxing the priors about the bounds of
yourself and having greatly elevated
plasticity and capacity for updating why
would you want something like this
those would be two cases where you'd
want it whether it's bringing basically
to basically bringing either
letting allowing a
a mother to care for the child long
enough to
help it to get past these early
milestones and also allowing potentially
mating pairs to stay together long
enough to help these hungry children to
the next generation
[ __ ] okay let's
let's get into that then so what would
the
the kind so there's some cup thing going
on here in terms of this kind of
turbocharging it's so
so in the sense it's kind of
psychologically adaptive to have relaxed
belief
over yourself over kind of yourself
model maybe even your autobiographical
self model
so as to facilitate
the advent of
another person into your life right so
that people just qualitatively talk
about how they now feel like this child
is their purpose they're kind of
secondary to this child in their life
so what's the kind of
what's the
causal pathway and what's the chronology
in this is it is it a
genetic adaptation that
um
occurs kind of simultaneously with like
modern childbirth
is or whatever that looks like or is it
um
does it predate it and then get sort of
exacted by
birthing start yeah birthing or does it
come later down the line what what what
I don't know actually how you would
examine that but what are you kind of
claiming in that regard
so
the specific
the specific mechanistic pathways
they were canalized in which ways
we got no idea so for instance like
you know there's there's all sorts of
things that could contribute like for
instance
uh
there seems to be for instance like the
the 2A receptor
you know in general it's actually fairly
insensitive relative to something like
the 1A receptor but if you take it and
expose it to like
reduced like blood like a rather reduced
blood pH or elevated acidity through
something like
hyperventilation like you know some kind
of things like carbon dioxide or lactic
acid accumulating
then it gets potentiated and so like for
instance like you know during
sexual activity during
uh
birth there will be a lot of heavy
breathing
over extended period and you know is
that actually like an accumulation of
carbon dioxide and actually that's part
of a mechanism of potentiation in these
receptors maybe we have no idea could it
involve something like endogenous DMT
maybe we have no idea could it involve
it as Sue is arguing
oxytocin and vasopressin in different
combinations quite possibly
but we we're just beginning that now in
terms of the specific pathways
but the in terms of when this might have
occurred and then
some more things that could have been
important
I'm wondering if there were like a
couple waves of strong selection one
probably with like the advent of
mammalian
reproduction in terms of like mammalian
care
so so the
you know once you're
now having to like going to earlier like
don't eat your child care for it you
know once you're getting to and and you
see in a lot of rodent species it's
actually you know a little bit tenuous
that process right like like the runt of
the litter often gets eaten you know
you're not that far from like the
atavistic state of kind of like
of um
so to get this interest like was it I
think Pat Churchland will actually talk
about like an extension of like
self-grooming to now
so for instance you could maybe think of
like actually like relaxing body maps
and then making them plastic for a time
on the occasion of birthing or like for
instance like during nursing
and then like basically if you then
include
the pup into the body of the your
offspring your body maps
like that could get them the count like
that off the ground
or then once you like for instance the
to the degree you get parental
investment you know so but this would
then be like a mammalian story and any
of those species there might have been
strong selection
on like these proto-psychedelic pathways
and then you know for then for humans
you know
it would be like all the things coming
together in terms of
having
you know the these big brains extremely
vulnerable hungry offspring which you
have to care for for a long time
often times also needing you know more
than one because part of it also of the
care is providing
you know protection within the social
hierarchy teaching them things you know
two heads being better than one
and so having the you know the bonding
of the parents for the child and the
parents to each other like now the
selection pressure might be really
strong what was selected
you know something involving oxytocin
potentially
in connection with DMT with other we got
no idea but
I guess the one more thing that could
happen
in um
not just in humans but maybe
particularly in humans
is our
our ability to
was it Jonathan Haidt talks about like
the hive mind switch
like our ability to actually like have
collective effervescence and to come
into like a group a sense of group
identity for the sake of basically
um
uh
doing things according to fashion
including beating out other groups
and so there seems to have been strong
selection on that in the human case also
and so the claim would be that these
like basically must pressures for
intersubjective
coupling
being particularly strong in humans
might have been a source of why for
instance um
uh
psychedelic experiences uh
but it would we're probably not the only
species to have them um but the idea
being that um
at least the reasons that we know that
we are sensitive to them some of that
could be because of that history of
selection
because of those challenges of of of
bonding between mating parents between
parents and children and potentially
between uh tribe.
Yeah, that that is really
um
it brings two things to mind. Um one is
I don't know whether you've ever heard
of the obstetrical dilemma.
Um which is basically this idea that
when humans went from being quadrupedal
to bipedal
the hips of the mother narrowed.
And what was happening is that there was
a lot of uh stillborn deaths a lot of
child birth deaths because the hips were
narrowing but the size of the baby's
head stayed the same so a lot of
children were dying in
um child birth a lot of moms mothers
were dying in child birth. And so there
was an evolutionary trade-off between um
early birth
and
bipedality.
And so what actually happens is is that
children start to get born younger
pregnancy is reduced in time
to
permit the narrowness of the hips that
allows for bipedality
which in turn
sets the stage for caregiving
and the fact that a child can't just pop
out of the womb like a gazelle and go
running.
So that's the one thing that comes to
mind. I'm going to include that in the
next paper.
Well, give me a shout-out. Um and then
the second
and then the second thing that makes me
think of is
maybe this care domain
this fundamental need to expand body
models self models
could be this kind of consciousness
synthetic a priori we were looking at.
Maybe there's an adaptive pressure to
feel
this kind of selfless love agape
whatever you want to call it towards
your offspring so as you know for
evolutionary reasons so that you are a
caring uh altruistic caregiver.
That's
I think potentially very
important for like so this
in the evolution of cognitive modernity
there seems to be a kind of like chicken
egg story or slight dilemma
where um you know
so like Chomsky like you know you know
you know you know talks about language
for the service of thought. But like and
so I guess that he somewhat side steps
the dilemma by saying like language is
just useful for structuring thought
right from the get-go.
Um but like let's say like you aren't
quite thinking that way so like language
is about communication like at first
like you or just you think you need that
to get like language use off the ground.
Well, then the question is like like um
but if you need language use to like who
are you communicating to?
And so like something that could
basically um
uh
scaffolds
um
uh the
so so in terms of like the the um
elaboration of uh forms of consciousness
and maybe like the even potentially like
the precision and the and the
uh
I don't know if you'd say richness but
like like even consciousness like
phenomenal consciousness in in its
qualities its ability to you know
represents like precise things
like
it it seems like in kind of
it seems like
if there's like a use
to being able to
feel your feelings in a way where you
can reflect on them in a way where they
can meaningfully uh
uh impact your behavior um if if that is
helping to um
basically provide some of the selection
uh
for certain
I don't know if this works but for
certain complexifications of
consciousness that that could
potentially help other places where you
might have chicken egg problems like
it's a source of preadaptation.
I guess that's what I'm wondering.
Yeah, exactly. I think that that's
exactly the line I was kind of shooting
down. Yeah.
this is
wonderful wonderful ideas. I guess
another question that comes to mind is
when people think about psychedelics
they probably don't think about relaxed
Bayesian priors they think about
tripping for want of a better word. They
think about hallucinations visions
auditory um
hallucinations as well.
So
in terms of the sort of adaptive
self-organizational
um
uh
functional utility of psychedelics that
all makes sense.
Why on earth do uh the sort of uh magic
dwarves or
uh recurring patterns or whatever
Terence McKenna was talking about what
what's going on there and and how does
that complexify the story?
So um
so before we get to machine elves and so
the part of the heterodox psychological
view
rather the heterodox active inference
view on psychedelics um would be that um
potentially those types of phenomena as
hallucinations or some forms of like you
might say psychodromic psychodromimetic
cognition or like the the um
you know
the entertaining of of a of a thought
that you would not normally under
entertain and you might think to be
crazy under other circumstances but that
is there live in your mind that you can
maybe think of
and some ways it seems to have like
almost the shape of a schizophrenic
delusion or like a proto psychotic
delusion.
Like it's so um you could potentially
argue for these as a relaxation of
high-level constraining beliefs allowing
those to be free form. But you could
also think of those as particularly
strong priors also that you're imposing
onto the world and not rather you're
you're now saying I'm going to I think
this is there this is my expectation
and I am not going to let that be
contract contradicted by sense data. And
so there's an so there's an
interpretation also in terms of a
strengthening of belief of those
phenomena you mentioned and one of the
points I'm trying to make in the paper
is I don't think we know how to think
about this. And so it's it's probably
some complex like admixture of relaxed
and strengthened beliefs both directly
and indirectly
in different combinations um where
I'm I guess trying to say that like um
rather than ever saying like
psychedelics do X
I want to replace that with um this
psychedelic uh this particular compound
at you know roughly at you know this
range of doses does this to this kind
this kind of person with these kinds of
set and settings. And the idea of saying
that like but the idea of like taking
inspiration from Rebus is like relaxed
beliefs being an essential feature in
some ways and looking to adjusting of
your priors in your mind is this like
belief ecosystem as a fruitful way of
like contextualizing psychedelic
functions. But then saying um moving
beyond relaxed beliefs but well like
both strengthened and relaxed in direct
and indirect ways. But to come along to
uh DMT elves that would be like an
example of like um
you know so you can say uh
you know uh
you can maybe think of that in a relaxed
belief story in that for instance you
know elves do not exist. And now I've
like relaxed certain aspects of my
ontology and now I've like made room for
these imaginings to arrive in a vivid
form like because of like um of an
indirect because I relaxed beliefs at at
this high level of certain core schemas
that like tell me what I should expect
in the world now I've made room for
psychedelic elves for instance or like
you know entities.
You could also tell a story though that
these are actually um kind of coming
back to core knowledge you know things
like um uh
you know um agenthood or agency or or
things like um
but maybe not even core knowledge like
just early lessons in the learning
curriculum and ongoing ones of just we
expect agents in the world cuz that's
the primary thing we're encountering
that's our primary niche is each other.
And so then basically for the beliefs so
like in a strengthened account you could
say let's say you're strengthening your
beliefs
maybe that you're the you're getting a
direct strengthening of these prime
these
priors for agency detection.
Are they evolutionary priors? Are they
developmental priors?
We have no idea. You know in my thinking
they tend to be more developmental but
it's you know it's a spectrum of how
you know where you want to how how how
much evolution shaping went into them.
And but
As as as our our conversation earlier um
yeah also I I stumbled across
uh you saying just these words which
really caught my eye archetypes as core
priors.
And I thought oh that's fantastic.
What a what a lovely way to put it. I
mean I guess I I I this is just this is
really really cool um really exciting.
I guess
so so just to piece together to scaffold
together the chronology the causality
the phenomenology
let's just like
try and put it all back together. So if
the original psychedelic experience
let's say was
uh child birth or orgasm
how does this end up
uh is it just a is it just a coincidence
that this ends up in plants?
Um,
and
if it is
is it informative that it was happening
in childbirth or um,
orgasm or is that just kind of a as I
was saying like a coincidental feature
of the activation of this receptor?
Um,
because you you you the argument that
you said though was earlier which is
that is a kind of defense mechanism or a
kind of uh,
attractor towards symbiosis is quite
convincing.
I guess we have to fold into all of this
the shamanic cultures and then the kind
of more modern therapeutic lens on uh,
psychedelics.
Is there a way of coalescing those
seemingly disparate strands?
So like for plants
like there's
the impact
that these signaling molecules
these different ones would have on the
plant itself and then on the other
systems that interact with them.
So for instance the um,
yeah, the 1A and the 2A receptors
will tend to have uh, different impacts
on cytoskeleton dynamics.
And so let's say you want to do
something like a phototaxis. Like the
like that actually it seems will involve
some um,
if I'm remembering correctly, I should
remember this precisely, but um,
there might even be like you can think
of it like um,
changing the cytoskeleton dynamics to
allow for greater fluidity.
You can maybe think of that as like a
kind of belief relaxation for more
morphogenetic inference of the plant. So
it's like you can you can think of the
plant as like you know, you know, doing
a phototaxis and it's you know, I'm
here, now I'm there.
You know, maybe you think of that as
like a kind of like
um,
uh,
updating for the plant itself.
And and maybe that's even part very
speculatively of why like you find it in
something like a cactus.
Where like that's actually kind of a
harder thing because you're blockier and
like you know, something like that.
But then the other aspect would be the
defense. Another reason you might have
it in something like a cactus is because
like if you're in the middle of the
desert and you're juicy, you you yeah,
uh,
you're extra tasty. You know, they're
like in terms of like there there is a
lot of game there there are a lot of you
know, contenders in town for things to
eat.
There's there's actually plenty
everywhere but still you're you're
you're you're a target. And you're
stationary. Um, by and large. You know,
so
then like you know, the which predators
were they targeting? It's like like
insects um,
you know,
what's happening to the belief dynamics
in the insect?
And so you know, at that level you know,
maybe you know, it's it's largely a uh,
uh,
um,
a
rebus accounts of the of like these
5HT2A agonists for the insects
potentially in terms of like
changing
uh,
their normal behavior. I'm not sure how
you would think of it there but like the
idea like you know, someone you know,
nibbles on you
um, it might be good for them to uh,
go away, become more exploratory and and
maybe even um, mate like crazy.
Like you you actually see something like
this in like locusts. Um, they have
they're colonized by hallucinogenic
fungi which can be part of their mating
cycle and is part of this like period of
intense mating they undergo.
And so you know,
you know,
you know, you the question is like why
not just poison them? You know, maybe
it's just like this was like the best
poison they came up with. It was good
enough that and it just did the job and
it it arrived by some means and just the
form of poisoning is um,
taking them the model the organism has
by which it is adaptive you relax that
model but that's not necessarily a good
thing for that that that that that
insect especially you know, with his
body weight you know, he's eating a lot
of it. And so the idea is that that
insect you know, if if it's if it's
models are really altered
and if those models are trying to
constrain all the different ways that
system can bifurcate to like be more
homogeneous and responsive and adaptive
ways um, you don't come out necessarily
ahead by doing that adaptively and so
that's just the way um,
insects figured out or that plants
figured out how to protect themselves.
Um, is and it it it's in the point of
the attack.
Uh, but maybe it's not even an attack.
Um, maybe it's like you want um,
yeah, it's
you know, it's fine if you nibble on me,
just don't nibble too much
and then uh,
but just go away
and then um,
and and and then if if we have this nice
relationship of you don't bother me too
much um,
you know, maybe I even like you to be
around. Maybe I even like that I
facilitated your mating and I like that
your genes are more prevalent in the
next generation.
So yeah, I guess and then coming to you
know, shamans Well, before before you do
just I'm curious about what you think
about this cuz
just like
add maybe a a technical end to this. I'm
curious about what you think
from a rebus account in the in this
case.
Because you mentioned exploratory
behavior there or epistemic foraging
which I thought was really an
interesting allusion.
Because in both cases you offered there
there's
a move towards epistemic behavior either
whether it's mating
and or you know, go away in an aversive
manner or go away um,
and basically like the reindeer example,
you know, spread me around basically in
a in a kind of weird way.
Like
right? Yeah, yeah, yeah. Well, that
screams spores.
Go forth. Right. And what that screams
to me
is
so it it's just in in the sense of like
the actual computational modeling in
POMDP schemes is
an emphasis over expected utility would
be sort of high precision over your B
and C schema.
Um,
and and E as well, your prior your
priors over action, your habits
basically.
And maybe what's happening here again,
it's a completely nascent thought that I
haven't given much
obviously uh, you know, thought to.
Is that
rela- you're you're relaxing your prior
beliefs about the consequences of your
action thereby making every single
possible action policy equal in terms of
epistemic utility.
Which means that you then maximum you do
some sort of Bayesian maximization of
entropy.
Which makes the best uh, in terms of
just the um,
expected free energy formula makes the
best action policy that which maximizes
information gain and or uh, test model
parameters.
So I'm wondering whether that speaks to
you in terms of a kind of technical
unpacking of what might you know, what
might be happening at a very um,
low level here with insects and cacti.
It would fit well
um,
with like changing migration patterns.
I think it would fit really well with
that. Um, in terms of uh, like
like think of like human use cases,
it seems like it's a mixture. Like so
for instance like um, so like
um,
sometimes you know, specifically would
be for um,
you know, breaking out of some state
you're caught in. Like you go to the
shaman and this is part of it. But often
times it would be like with a very
specific interest in mind. Like um, who
someone cursed my cow, who is it? You
know, or or like but or sometimes it
would be like um, uh,
uh,
so sometimes it seems like there's a
good amount about like the epistemics in
terms of about like trying to maximize
learning and breaking you free from like
the thing
that is usually owning you from within.
You know, like your usual
way of achieving your goals keeping you
stuck in a certain pattern and then it's
like you need to learn something
different but how are you going to learn
something different if you're always
doing the same thing again and again?
And so
I think that fits for a lot of the like
a lot of the healing uses
that accompany like like an ayahuasca
ceremony that that seems like a good
description. But there are like other
use cases like for instance like in like
um, I think it's Amazonian tribes like
uh, it's actually like specifically
pragmatic in that like
they do it to to get the hunting party
together. And like like they'll
uh, they're about to go to war with a
specific other tribe. But then you could
also though make a case of like
um, you know,
is it that like
they're like their goal of what they
want to do when they encounter the other
tribe, you want that to be presented in
a very vivid form of that imagining, you
want that counterfactual to be hyper
precise so that it becomes actual?
Or is it um, more like a matter of like
this kind of collective effervescence
from earlier? And you actually want a
rebus account so that before you go into
battle, you're basically you know, all
one body according together fighting,
you know, having each other's backs and
um,
or both. And you want but you know, an
early stage of something rebus like and
then maybe a later stage of something
more uh, involving
belief strengthening. So it's like
sometimes you're letting go of the
pragmatics and sometimes you're actually
like holding it on to the
the um, pragmatic value and specifically
zooming into it.
Um,
it it seems like
there like at least the human case there
is no singular account. But in terms of
you're saying about like things like um,
uh,
like the the case of an like migration
patterns in an animal being changed. Um,
that seems like it that that that that
be relaxing the pragmatics and allowing
the epistemics to to allow more
optimization for that that
that could be a a really important part
of that I think. Cool.
Amazing. Yeah, I mean
we haven't got too much time left, but
um
I guess
two more questions. One totally trivial,
the other one not trivial at all. So,
I'll start with the non-trivial one.
Um
At Johns Hopkins, you're you're really
at the heart of the current uptick in
psychedelic research.
Are you
Well, just to frame this
I sense
from an external perspective there was a
great deal of excitement
you know, starting 5 6 7 years ago.
And maybe now there's a
um there's a slight conservatism that's
crept in and and and saying, "Okay, the
the psychedelics might not be the
panacea that we hoped it might have been
7 or 8 years ago." Again, I'm not on the
inside. I don't know, but that's just my
instinct.
What what are your kind of uh
predictions, expectations, level of
optimism with respect to psychedelic
therapy in the next 10 20 30 years?
Um
I have some
uh
So, if we can avoid the very live
possibility of uh
backlash as
um
uh adverse outcomes happen inevitably,
and they will be more notable. It's you
know, like with driverless cars. Like,
if you know, even if on net they're
saving lives, you will note those cases
where it just slams into, you know, a
person, and you'll just be and that'll
change everything. And so, it doesn't
take many people to have some really bad
experiences.
Um they even see like with the recent
like uh Matthew Perry, like what
happened with him. Although, yeah, and
and that really is I'm actually really
deeply responsible for everyone involved
because
um you I don't want to say that you
know, like ketamine's, you know, uh not
a mixed uh like like it's a powerful
medicine. And and but uh and in that
case, like um you know, you see you see
the shape of it. There's already like
people are interpreting this as, "Oh,
ketamine is dangerous." And already this
has caused people to call for more
of a pullback, but he was also on a a
good dose of an opiate, um probably has
some drinking in his system, and was in
a hot tub. So,
you know, so it's like um
you know, did he die of respiratory
depression and then drowned? You know,
it's uh
Anyways, but so things like that can
happen, and
uh
it doesn't take many of those for the
psychedelic renaissance to really be
like pulled back into our potential like
life-changing uh
medicines, interventions.
Um oh, by the way, uh whenever I'm
speaking, it's um
outside of a Hopkins position. So,
they and they are at um
so, speaking from the outside. Um uh
they have a particular role, I'd say, in
in the psychedelic renaissance of doing
largely conservative work within a
mainstream medical model, and trying to
say, "Can we push forward that?" And the
and and and and how can we approach
these medicines safely and responsibly?
And so, um they tend to be I I'd say
more conservative in what they're doing,
and it's a very valuable function.
Um and and so, uh you know, and in
general, they they try to be very
careful. I'm
I'm a little less careful.
Um
so, uh
the um
Some of the things that are So, some of
the open questions and and challenges we
have is uh what
um
I guess you say business models or how
can we scale psychedelic therapy? So, I
said one of the problems with like a
like a psilocybin and um intervention
is that they're amazingly expensive.
And so, the question is like, how can we
get like broad access to them? You need
some sort of like group therapy and like
a different model than the ones we
currently use just to make the economics
work, to make this like an available
one, a widely available intervention. Um
the other question is like, if you
remove some of the um expectancy effects
you would get from like the places where
these interventions were done, and like
um you know, the you know, having it
done at Johns Hopkins, you know, the the
like the um or the Good Friday
experiment you know,
in Harvard, there's a certain trust and
authority which is interacting with this
as part of like leading up to it, that's
part of like the expectation that you
will be so changed.
And so, if you then try to, you know,
have clinics opening up everywhere, do
you get the same effect? Because you
you'll have, you know, the reports, you
know, is some of the five most
meaningful experiences in a person's
life. A few sessions, your life is
changed. And to what extent can we still
get outcomes like that um as we move
into basically scaling and and having
more institutions and more contexts, and
and do so safely?
One of the things I'm actually very
excited about is I have some uh friends
in um pharmaceuticals who are basically
creating analogs of these psychedelic
compounds to try to change their
property slightly. And so, one of them
is like, for instance, um uh
uh shortening their duration of action.
And well, why would you want to do that?
Well, let's say like you could show up
for a therapist, and you can do
basically MDMA therapy, and be sober
again in 2 hours. Mm.
And so, that would both allow you
basically to do it um more flexibly, do
it uh and do it more times potentially,
and you know, and with less risk from
the dose because things like
excitotoxicity will be a function of
both the dose and the duration of
effect. And so, if you do such a
duration of effect, things like, you
know, um metabolic strain is you would
reduce it. So,
those advances I think are going to be
complete game-changer. Like,
uh
the the short-acting powerful compounds
uh I think psychiatry will not be the
same once those are on the scene, and
just countless lives will be saved and
transformed. Fantastic. So, yeah, and
so, there's a lot of like things are
very fraught, right? You know, we could
have something like a couple bad
outcomes could cause like a a chill on
the whole thing.
But the promise if we could just make it
through this crucible, I think it's
unbelievable. Amazing. Well, that's
exciting. And then my my super trivial
question, especially even more trivial
given that response is um
ayahuasca is uh famously kind of an
enigma
um because it's you you may correct me
on my uh chemist my biochemistry here.
But isn't it
DMT
mixed with a plant
among the hundreds of thousands of
plants that are found or could be found
in the Amazon.
What's your
Joe Rogan-esque
thoughts on how on earth they managed to
synthesize ayahuasca? Yeah, you have
your your edible DMT, but that'll be
broken down in a hot minute.
And so, you need to find basically this
monoamine oxidase inhibitor to keep it
going. But among all the different
things you could have tried, how did
they find the right one? Quite Yeah. The
shamans would tell would totally tell
you the plants told us. Ah. That's how
they did it. That doesn't help.
Um
I guess, you know,
I'm hoping I don't maybe we should get
like Joe Hire on the job, and like
basically some sort of computational
model of like
the process of like trying out the
permutations of like what shamans do
normally. Mm.
Uh
maybe it's actually tractable in terms
of like if you see just what they're
doing, it's like, yeah, they were going
to find that given what they were doing
in like
over over 200 years, you would expect at
this percent that they found it. So, I I
would expect something kind of like
that, or maybe the plants told them. Or
maybe the plants told them.
Yeah, maybe. Adam, that was that was
amazing.
I'm kind of mind-blown. Um
that was awesome. Thank you so much. I
I mean, with every guest, I always feel
like I learn just
infinite sums of new information
which makes this so much fun for me.
Um but no, I really thank you. I I know
you're a busy man, and so I'm very
grateful for you giving me 2 hours of
your time.
Um
it was a pleasure.
We're going to we're going to keep
digging away at these questions.
Um but yeah, for me and the issue, yeah,
it was it was an absolute uh pleasure on
my part. So, thank you again.
Thank you. All right.
Thanks.